Guide to the Laura Oren Papers
University of Houston Libraries
Laura Oren Papers
1970-1979
02/2005-001
Oren, Laura
2.00 linear feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
This collection consists of 7 series and is housed in 2 boxes. The focus of the papers is the various organizations with which Oren has been affiliated. Most notably, this collection includes organizational material regarding the Houston Area Feminist Federal Credit Union, the National Organization for Women and Women and Labor organizations.
Biographical Information:
Professor Laura Oren received her first degree from Queens College, The City University of New York in 1966 as a Magna Cum Laude graduate. She holds a Ph.D. in British History from Yale University and graduated first in her class from the University of Houston Law Center in 1980. After graduation, she worked in private practice, specializing in civil rights law and appellate work.
As a University of Houston Law Center faculty, she teaches Family Law and Constitutional Law and most of her work has often been about the intersection of these two fields. Additionally, she teaches Women and the Law, Conflict of Laws, and State and Local Government Law. Her specialty areas of research are in Civil Rights and Family Law.
In addition to her work as a lawyer and a professor of law, Oren has been very active in the women’s rights movement. She was involved with the National Organization for Women, the National Women’s Conference in Houston, and the Houston Area Feminist Federal Credit Union.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
University of Houston -- Faculty; University of Houston. Law Center -- Alumni and alumnae
Genre/Form of Material:
Brochures; Correspondence; Newsletters; Pamphlets; Photographs; Publications (document genre)
Personal Name:
Oren, Laura
Topical Term:
Feminism; Feminists; Women's rights
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of 7 series and is housed in 2 boxes. The focus of the papers is the various organizations with which Oren has been affiliated. Most notably, this collection includes organizational material regarding the Houston Area Feminist Federal Credit Union, the National Organization for Women and Women and Labor organizations.
Detailed List of Contents
- Women and Labor Information & Organizations, 1973-1979
  Scope and Contents
  Various organizations and information pertaining to labor rights have been put together in this series.
  - Coalition of Labor Union Women (CLEW) (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Coalition of Labor Union Women, Houston Chapter (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Federally Employed Women (FEW) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - International Union of Electrical, Radio & Machine Workers (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - United Automotive Workers (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - U.S. Department of Labor (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Equal Employment Opportunity Act Reprints (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Women & Labor Miscellaneous Information (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Newsletters and Information, 1970-1977
  Program details about women studies at different universities and newsletters of several organizations have been compiled together.
  - Women's Rights Coordinating Council & Newsletters (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Women Studies at Rochester University (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Coordinating Council for Women in Historical Profession & Newsletter (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
  - Women's Studies Program at Various Universities (Box 1, Folder 15-18)
  - Trade Union Women Studies (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
  - Nikki Van Hightower (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Formation of City Women's Employees Organization (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Formation of “Women’s Right to Choose”, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - National Abortion Right's Action League Information (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Miscellaneous Newsletters & Magazines (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Feminist Information, 1970-1977
  Creative writings, feminist material and newspaper clippings, calendars and other published information is compiled together in this series.
  - Brochures and Pamphlets, 1971-1977 (Box 1, Folder 26-28)
  - Annotated Calendars, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Clippings, 1972-1977 (Box 1, Folder 30-31)
  - Creative Writings, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Feminist Material, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 33-34)
  - Women’s Health Information (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Suggested Readings, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Manuscripts- Plans/Notes (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Equal Rights Amendment (ERA) Literature, 1973-1977
  Newspaper clippings, brochures etc. along with information regarding equal rights amendment is housed.
  - Equal Rights Amendment Literature (Box 2, Folder 38)
- National Organization for Women
  Information regarding national organization for women, financial documents, correspondence with the parent body are the highlights of this series.
  - National Organization for Women (Box 2, Folder 39)
- National Women’s Conference, Houston Information, 1977
  The famous national women’s conference at Houston is the highlight of this series. It houses the program brochure, proposed national plan of action at the conference, special issue of WOMEN, 1977.
  - National Women’s Conference, Houston 1977, Information (Box 2, Folder 40)
- Houston Area Feminist Federal Credit Union (HAFFCU) Records, 1972-1978
  It is split into 6 distinct folders which contain the organizational documents along with the financial documents and board meetings, photographic material and other literature form part of this series.
  - Houston Area Feminist Federal Credit Union (HAFFCU) Records (Box 2, Folder 41-46)